<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sins of a gainsaying and rebellious people laid before them ... Also a word to foolish merchants ... / Written at the command of the Lord, by one of his servants called, John Rous.</title>
            <author>Rous, John, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182860</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789395</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2646:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sins of a gainsaying and rebellious people laid before them ... Also a word to foolish merchants ... / Written at the command of the Lord, by one of his servants called, John Rous.</title>
                  <author>Rous, John, d. 1695.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the 4th. month 8th. day for M.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: G.F. [i.e. George Fox?].</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The ſins of a gainſaying and rebellious people laid before them, that if there be any tenderneſs in them, they may repent, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their wickedneſs, and return to the Lord, before the grievous ſtorm of the fury of the Lord ouertake them, in which, all the wicked and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ones, ſhall be overwhelmed.</head>
            <head type="sub">Alſo a word to fooliſh Merchant, looſe profeſſours, and ungodly parents, who train up their children in wickedneſs: Written at the command of the Lord, by one of his ſervants called, <hi>John Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>OVer you O ye ſcattered people in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> do I lament; O how have ye refuſed to be healed! O how have ye deſpiſed healing. O how have ye deſpiſed the Love of God, which hath long and often been proffered unto you! O how have ye turned the grace of God into lafciviouſneſs! and like Swine have delighted in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in filthineſs, your abommable practiſes have ye gloried in, and have made a ſport of wickedneſs, ſporting in your dallying and wantonneſs, out of the fear of the Lord, ſpending your time in pleaſures, and in vain delights, living as the beaſts of the field without the knowledge of God, committing idolatry, eating and drinking, and riſing up to play, which thing is abominable in the ſight of God; O how is the image of the Devil exalted among you! and the image of God defaced and utterly loſt, ſo that there is no mark of it to be ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, but the image of the Divel how plainly is it diſcovered among you, even in all places where you are, the ſwearer by his ſwearing ſhews whoſe image he bears, the lyar by his lying, ſhews who is his father, the drunkard by his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs ſhews what he delights in, and what God he ſerveth, the deceitful man by his deceit ſhews he knows not the image of God, the oppreſſour whoſe life is wicked, and whoſe end is accurſed ſhews what a diveli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h wicked ſpirit he is gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by, who to get to himſelf cares not what thoſe that are under him ſuffers, who to get of the earth into his poſſeſſion, and increaſe his unrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> (which is his God whom he ſerves) cares not what murder is committed by him to fulfil his unrighteous and covetous ends, (I ſpeak concerning you, who like unnatural beaſts have been the death of many of your ſervants, by withholding from them convenient food, for want of which many have periſhed under you, but his <hi>Mammon</hi> will not ſave him in the day of the Lord, for that, for which (like a fool) he hath ventured his ſoul and loſt it to get, will not purchaſe him one drop of cold water in hell to cool his tongue with: and truely ye ſwearers, covetous lyars, cozners, deceitful ones, and oppreſſors, thither muſt ye go, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye repent, the Divel whom ye now ſerve cannot deliver you, ye he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over you when you come thither, as he doth now at your preſent folly, who follow him in the broad way which leads to deſtruction, which ye earneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y follow, but ye conſide not that the end of it is torment, out of which there ſhall be no redemption; how have ye deſpiſed the voice of God? how have ye deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the call of the Lord to repentance, and have hardned your hearts againſt the loving kindneſs of God, which hath been profered to you day after day, and time after time, ye have deſpitefully uſed thoſe who have been ſent unto you, and accounted them your friends who have daubed you up with deceit; you have been bold for your idol-dumb ſhepherds, who have been cur, ſed examples to you of wickedneſs and prophaneneſs, in ſwearing in drunkenneſs, in rioting in quar, relling, in lyings in diſſembling, theſe men who have lived in theſe wicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172706:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>are thoſe whom ye have accounted your friends, and for your love to theſe, the ſervants of the Lord, who have been ſent to warn you, have ye deſpitefully uſed, ſome with ſcoffs and reproaches, ſome with blowes and punches, and ſome with ſhedding their blood, as I am a witneſs againſt you, and being wilfully mad, many of you have ſaid (when ye have taken thoſe who have been ſent unto you, and uſed them according to your unreaſonable wills) hang them, others have ſaid hanging is too good for them, and this is becauſe they lay before you your wickedneſs, and declare againſt your ſervice, wherewith you mock God and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour his name, for if Turks and Indians ſhould ſee your violence and madneſs (as hath been declared to you) into which you fly forth (either before, in or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your ſervice, if any of the ſervants of the Lord come among you, would they not cry ſhame on you? and think it ſtrange that ſuch ſhould talke of a pure and holy God, who act ſo filthily; be aſhamed ye wicked ones to take the name of God into your mouthes, who hate to be reformed, who hate to be reproved, who hate to return from your filthineſs, ſit down and lament ye careleſs ones, caſt off your garments of mirth and joy, and take unto you ſackloath, humble your ſelves leſt ye be deſtroyed; for behold the day is coming and neer at hand, that your joy and rejoycing ſhall fly far from you, and hovvling and lamenting ſhall overtake you, vvhich ye ſhall not be able to fly from, for behold a ſtorm of thunder and great hail, and a day of terrour and thick darkneſs ſhall come upon the vvicked, vvhich none ſhall be able to deliver them from, neither from it ſhall they be able to deliver themſelves, but in it ſhall be overwhelmed, if ye ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to go on in vvickedneſs, ye ſhall periſh, none ſhall be ſaved but thoſe vvho repent, none ſhall be delivered but thoſe vvho return to the Lord, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn vvhile you have time, returne before the overflovving ſcourge doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you, vvhich ſhall ſvveep avvay the refuge of lies, vvith all vvho put their truſt in it, no ſuch refuge vvill ſtand before the Lord, and vvoe unto you that fly not to him for refuge, no place vvill be found to hide the great ones of the earth from the preſence of the Lambe though they cry to the Mountains and hills to fall upon them, yet ſhall they not be hid, for their refuge ſhall be ſvvept avvay, though ye fly to your teachers for refuge, yet ſhall they not deliver you, for then vvill their filthineſs appear, and they vvill have ſo much need of a hiding place as you, though novv they flatter you and call you Chriſtians, vvhile ye are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God and his vvaies, and ye call them Miniſters of Chriſt, and fight for them, yet the deceiver and the deceived ſhall periſh together, vvithout ſpeedy repentance, the blind leaders, and the blind that follow them, ſhall both fall into the ditch together, who return not, lift up your eyes on high, and behold how your iniquities hang over your heads, as a black cloud, behold how the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God is ready to fall upon you, vengeance in flames of fire you muſt expect who are wicked, the cup of the Lords fury is filled for you, who have made your faces as braſs, and hearts as ſtone againſt the Lord; ye ſhew by your perverſneſs what generation you are of, ye are of that generation which alwaies reſiſted the holy Ghoſt, who alwaies fought againſt God, who alwaies reproched the truth, who alwaies were enemies to God, and children of the Divel, ye bear the image of him who hath begotten you, and ye cannot abide to hear his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome declared againſt, and therefore do ye imagine a vain thing, and are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therd together againſt God and his Chriſt, but kiſs the ſon leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, for if his anger be but a little kindled, bleſſed are thoſe that put their truſt in him, but woe unto them that truſt not in him, ſave your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172706:2"/>ſelves by ſpeedy repentance, and think not becauſe repentance is profered unto you, therefore it may be time enough to repent when ye have ſerved the Divel ſo long as ye can, for verily none of you know how ſoon ye may be cut off, none of you can ſay ye ſhall live a month longer, and how can ye then ſay ye will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent half a year or a year hence, or more, this is the way where in the divel leads you, ye put off repentance till ſuch a time, and think ye will repent then, but when the time is come, the abominable practiſes are beloved as much, yea it may be more then they were before; and none of you are ſo ignorant but ye know that except ye repent ye ſhall all periſh, and conſider what a ſad condition that will be, would it not make you tremble and quake if you did truely conſider of it though none now are more the objects of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, and ſcorn, and malice, then thoſe that tremble at the preſence of the Lord, take heed to your ſelves, it is better to loſe the joye of the world for a time then loſe your own ſouls for ever: will flattering of your ſelves ſave you? will ſaying that the Lord is with you and no evil ſhall befall you (while you live in filthineſs and uncleanneſs) deliver you? will not the Lord puniſh you and your ſhepheards, together for the abominations of your holy things? will crying Lord Lord, we have profeſſed thy name, and talked much of the Scriptures, and have ſpoken much of thy truth, ſave you in the day of the righteous judgement of God, from going into hell with the Divel and his Angels? which is a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for all the wicked, nay be not deceived, ye muſt be regenerate and born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, or, cannot inherit the kingdome of God; your proud hearts ye proud ones muſt come down, before ye receive Chriſt who is humble, without whom no ſalvation ye can witneſs, ye envious ones, your envious natures muſt be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred and forſaken, before he who is the Covenant of God, who is love, is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in you; drunkards, you muſt forſake your drunkenneſs and learn moderation, before Jeſus Chriſt ye do witneſs, who teaches moderation in all things, without vvhom ye cannot pleaſe God; and ye who are covetous, who are griping for the earth, your idolatry you muſt come to forſake before ye knovv Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vvithout vvhom all is accurſed and ye will be left poor, and naked, and miſerable, though by violence you have inlarged your poſſeſſions, and made your ſelves great in the earth.</p>
               <p>O conſider ye Merchants, who are ſelling that which is ſpiritual for that which is carnal, who are ſelling the health of your ſouls, to ſatisfie your covetous minds and are ſelling the everlaſting inheritance to get wealth in the earth, ye are fooliſh and not wiſe; ye have not yet learned the true wiſdome, ye have ſpent your time in vain, if ye come to caſt up your accounts ye will find it ſo, ye have loſt by your trading and not gained, there is a pearle whoſe price ye know not, ſeek after it for it is pretious, and when ye have found it, ſell all ye have as yet got to purchaſe it, ſo ſhall ye have gain enough, and abundance of riches, yea, the price of that pearl cannot be caſt up, therefore no longer ſpend your time for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not, but come unto him where ye may have enough of all things and aboundance of riches; for while ye come not to witneſs the godly pearl, ye never have enough, though you could purchaſe the whole vvorld; but being poſſeſſed of this pearl, you will have enough of all things; truely I cannot but ſorrow for you who deſpiſe it, and think that a little of the earth is better then this pearl, it is becauſe you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and ſottiſh and have not accounted right, you have overpriſed that which is not worthy to be eſteemed, and have undervalued that which is alone to
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:172706:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>be priſed, like <hi>Eſau</hi> ſell your birthright for a meſs of Pottage, caſt up your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts again, and reckon rightly, for the Lord is coming to call you to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then will it be known whether ye have been faithful ſervants, who have gained with your Lords money by trading: conſider betimes, for he is near at hand who will call you to an account, it will not be enough for you to ſay that the Lord is a hard maſter, that will not ſave you from being caſt into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who are wicked and ſloathful ſervants; if there be any among you who is wiſe, let his wiſdome appear in preparing to meet the Lord by ſpeedy repentance by putting away drowſineſs, and doing that which is juſt.</p>
               <p>And now ye drowſy profeſſours, who are found in the abominable practiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, who have taſted of the goodneſs of God, and have made much mention of his Name, ye are to be ſharply reproved above others, for ye have known that which others for want of the knowledge of have periſhed; your ſin is greater then others, your abomination is aggravated in a far higher meaſure then others, for others have beenbold to do wickedly, having you for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to them, others have ſaid within themſelves, may not I be covetous, proud, wanton, and ſcornful, for ſuch a one is ſo, who hath more knowledge then I have, and thus through your looſeneſs have ye cauſed the name of the Lord to be blaſphemed, yea are to be beaten with many ſtripes, becauſe ye knew the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will out did it not; ye knew that ptide the Lord did abhorr, ye knew you ſhould not be wanton, ye knew that covetouſneſs is idolatry, theſe things ye knew but practiſed not, therefore your condemnation will be greater; ceaſe from your dead images which you are ſeeking to put life into by your ſubtile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, your images are to be broken and ye are to be ſcattered, if there be any of your former honeſty, and zeale towards God remaining in you, return be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fury of the Lord break forth to conſume his enemies vvho truſt not in him, be aſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>med of your levvdneſs and impudence, and take unto you modeſty, and talk not of the condition of the ſaints no further then you can vvitneſs them fulfilled in you; call not God Father, till you can vvitneſs that vvhich is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God doth rule you, conſider hovv ye have blaſphemed the name of God, vvhile you have called him Father and Lord, but have done the vvorks of the Divel, conſider hovv the vvay of truth hath been evill ſpoken of through your looſneſs, vvho have called your ſelves by the name of God and Chriſt, yet novv are found talking of and pleading for the liberty of the fleſh; O be aſhamed and confounded, is this the end of your profeſſion? is this the end of your talk? is the liberty of the fleſh that wch. ye have been contending for all this while? will God be thus ſerved? will not he be avenged on ſuch a generation as this? who hath thus deceitfully dealt with him; take heed ye are not ſtronger then God; what will become of this chaffe, when he who is a conſuming fire ſhall plead with it? will this abide the fire? will this ſtand before the Lord? pure is his name, pure is his power, let all that defiles and works abominations depart from him, for it cannot dwell vvith him, neither doth he delight in it; therefore O ye profeſſors, vvho are lifted up in a dead unſavoury, and putrified profeſſion, come dovvn and depart from your filthineſs which ye have long lived in, or for ever you muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the preſence of God; ye are like tall Cedars, but your boughs vvill be lopped, and your beautiful branches (wherewith you have deceived many who have admited your beauty) ſhall be taken from you, then ſhall the old ſtump from whence theſe branches have grown, be ſeen to be as wood fit for the fire; your profeſſion is diſcovered, and your nakedneſs is ſeen, therefore repent while you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172706:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>have time, and it is a day of viſitation to you.</p>
               <p>And now O ye parents who have many children, conſider vvhat it is children are given you for; is it to bring them up in pride, and idleneſs, vvantonneſs and luxury? do ye herein diſcharge the duty of parents? ſhould ye not have ſought the Lord your ſelves, and have inſtructed your children in his fear, this ye ſhould have done, but contrarily, you have forſaken the Lord your ſelves, &amp; wrought wickedneſſe, and have brought up your children in your own abominations, in pride, in wantoneſſe, in diſdain, in deceit, and whatſoever is abominable in the ſight of God; muſt ye not give an account for theſe things? muſt ye not anſwer for your children, whom ye have cauſed to go aſtray, how hath goodneſs been hated by you? even ſo that many of you, yea for the moſt part, if there hath ben any tender in any of your children, and if any of them have turned, abſide in any meaſure from following your wicked ſteps, then hath it been your work to ſmother thoſe deſires, and have cryed out of melancholy, and ſay that children ſhould be merry and laugh, and ſuch like; and thus vvalk in the broad way your ſelves, and bring up your children to follow your own ſteps; how will ye give an account before the Lord? how will you anſwer for theſe things before him, who will puniſh you for theſe things? How many is there among you who have been forward in teaching their children to curſe and ſwear, and in hearing them to be ready at it, have been delighted? have not many of you taught your children to lye and diſſemble, and have called them good children, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n they have been expert at it? O horrible wickedneſs! vvas ever any like this? is it not a ſhame that ſuch a thing ſhould be named, much leſſe practized by thoſe who call themſelves chriſtians? will not the Heathen who have not heard of God, riſe up in iudgement vvith this generation, and condemn them for their filthineſs.</p>
               <p>Now to the light of Chriſt in all your conſciences do I appeal (which doth condemne theſe wicked practiſes before mentiond) whether theſe things be not ſo, the teſtimonie of that ſeek, for that will not lye, though yee will, and is a teacher to all who follow it, and are guided by it, but is for ever the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of all who deſpiſe and diſobey it, and remember that your ſins have been laid before you, ye ſtubborn ones, who hate to be reformed, and now the time is paſt, and ye are in the pit, out of which there is no redemption, remember that a day was profered to you, and that there was a time wherein it was ſaid to you, to day if you will hear his voice, harden not yur hearts, So I reſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>This written to the uncircumciſed in hearts and ears, who go on in the Stiff-neckedneſs of their own hearts, deſpiſing the Love of the Lord, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſpite unto his Spirit.</dateline>
                  <signed>A ſufferer for the ſake of the ſeed of God and a friend of Sions peace, for which I am hated by the inhabitants of Babylon, both prieſts, and people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſors and prophane, known by the name, <hi>John Rouſe.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>A Prayer concerning ſuch as are made Miniſters by the II of man, and a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exhortation to all ſober minded people to come out from among them.</p>
               <p>Vhat miniſtery is that which is upheld by a Law given forth in mans will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray to the Law of God, if it be not Antichriſtian? and whether or no their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172706:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Miniſtery was from God that haled out of the Synogoues, or thoſe that were haled? And whether <hi>Paul</hi>'s Miniſtery was not according to what you now perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, who went into the Synagogues to reaſon with them, after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as wee doe novv, vvho received not his Miniſtery from man, neither had it by man, though he was brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliell,</hi> he counted that which he learned there, as dung and droſſe, in compariſon of the excellency of Jeſus Chriſt; and now with the Same light, your form of prayer, and form off preaching without the power, it is as droſſe and dung to me, and to all that live in the life, who know Chriſt to be the high Prieſt over the houſhold of God, whoſe Government is on his ſhoulders, who will not acquit the wicked, neither ſhall the evill doer eſcape his hand; for the hand of the Lord is ſtreched out, and by the bareing of his arme are we Saved from all our trang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſions, which by no other means could be done; for when I wallowing in my blood, and no eye pittied me, nor none could cure my diſeaſe, when I went through the vale of miſery, in the cloudy and dark day, when no light appeared, then was I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing men, but darkneſs was over the whole earth in me, which was my great ſorrow, but ſometimes hope was an anchor, that it ſhould not be alwaies ſo, but when the flood came I was as one overwhelmed with ſorrow, for all my actings, and my prayers returned in vain; while I was acting for life, the living ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in me, which groaned for deliverance, and the groans of that was heard, and not my prayers, then the Son of Righteouſneſs appeared to me, with healing under his wings, then he rent the vail, and uncovered all that I had done, and ſhewed me the book wherein all my actions were ſet down, that I had acted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him ever ſince I was a childe, and indeed I could read in it, and knew what was written there, then was the acceptable yeer of the Lord God, and the day of vengeance to the ungodly in me, then was the vials of the wrath of God powred forth upon me without mixture, and indeed it was given me to drink deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but I deſired that I might be ſpared, but it was to let me ſee that I had Sinned againſt God, and I ſhould bear his indignation, untill he did plead my cauſe, for I was condemned, but the Blood of the Son of God ranſomed me and brought me into freedom, which by no other meanes could be done; then he ſhewed me his doctrine, and writ his Law in me, and placed his word in my heart, which is an everlaſting witneſs for himſelf, and againſt all the world, that their deeds are evil, who by his power hath ſhaken, and cauſed all my bones to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to ſtagger like a drunken man, but the remainder of himſelf could not be Shaken, for he was ſtricken, and by his ſtripes were we healed, and by his light we ſee all hirelings, and perſecutors to be out of his doctrine; therefore we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them; So all people who fear God come out from among them (leaſt yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be partakers of their plagues) as I have done. <hi>M. F.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The difference between the worlds relation which ſtands in ſtrife, malice and wickedneſſe, and the Saints relation which ſtands in love, life, peace and joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>The Relation which ſtands in deſtroying, is by the children of the light denie, all ſuch who live out of light, and out of it walke, who wear the old garmet, whoſe minde is corrupt, and hath a wiſdome; and with it know not God, ad hath a knovvledge &amp; with it corrupt themſelves, &amp; hath a humility, but feiged, and hath a worſhip but in the will, and hath a righteouſneſſe but in the ſelf; nd ſpeaks the high words but it is in hipocriſie, and hath a liberty but in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, where the ſpirit is in priſon, who in <hi>Caines</hi> way is gone, and hath not a habitaion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172706:4"/>in God, whoſe affections are below in the earth, and ſerve the luſts and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, whoſe converſation is among the wicked, and there is the worlds relation where lodgeth the ſtrife and the debate and deceit, and diſdain, and ſetting up that which God will throw down, now vvhile this is ſtanding which is contrary to the light, they that in the light do vvalke, and be in it, theſe hey deny, and Sees that vvhich leads nature out of its courſe, and vvhat ſets the vvhole courſe of nature on fire, and there the vvhole vvorld are in confuſion, and all the tongues are unbridled, vvhere povver over them is not, vvhile that reignes vvhich leads nature out of courſe, his religion is vain, and that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſtands out of truth, but all ſuch as to the light are turned, See vvith the light (and that doth manifeſt vvhat leadeth nature out of courſe,) the mariage that is honourable, and vvhat ſets the vvhole courſe of nature on fire, and vvhat leads nature into courſe, vvhere the pure relation and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of it is received, vvhere the ſelf and its righteouſneſs is denied, and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt received, vvhere the vvorſhip of the vvill is denied, and the vvorſhip of God in Spirit and Truth received, vvhere ſelf righteouſnes is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and Chriſt the righteouſneſs of God received, &amp; the former converſation put of &amp; the converſation in Heaven vvitneſſed, the affections belovv changed, &amp; the affections vvhich are above come to; here is the pure Religion knovvn vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out guile, vvhich are out of <hi>Cains</hi> vvay, vvhere the habitation in God is vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed and ſeen, vvhere the juſt lives by his faith, and honouring in the Lord knovvn, and the true humility Learned of Chriſt, vvho is not of the vvorld, though it by him vvas made, vvho lighteth every man that cometh into the vvorld, vvho is mans vvay out of it; vvhich light is mans condemnation if he do not beleeve in it; and the relation vvhich is in the vvorld (vvho hate the light,) is in the luſt, where the perverſenes is in the love of the world, vvhere the envy is, vvhere the invention is, ſelfeiſhneſs, croſſeneſſe, perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, back-biting, maliciouſnes, filling with unrighteouſneſs, yet they have a love, yet they have a relation, now the light which comes from the beloved Son of God, where the Love of God is received, the worlds relation is denied, for the relation of the world deſtroyes and devoures, but the children of the light, which be in the relation out of the World, live in peace, unity, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and comfort enjoyed in the holy Ghoſt, ſo all you that profeſſe relation in words, and envy lodgeth in your hearts againſt one another, and yet flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one another to your faces, and backbite one another, behinde the back, ſuch relations we deny, and have a witneſs in your conſciences againſt it; And all that profeſs a relation one to another, and love and friendſhip with the tongue, and in heart deceive one another, and cozen, and cheat one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and lie, and diſſemble one with another, all ſuch relations we deny, and have a witneſs in your conſcience againſt it: And ſuch as profeſſe religion, or worſhip, or humility, righteouſneſs, and the Scripture, Chriſt and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets words, &amp; live out of their life, and live in envy and malice, and yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe you have a relation to Chriſt, and God, whom ye have not ſeen, and you love him, and do not love them whom you have ſeen, ſuch relations we do denie; &amp; all ſuch as cry up your experiences, high notions, manifeſtations, as you call them, diſpenſations as you call them, and live in pride, ſtrife, and envy, debates, deriſion, ſcornes, loftineſs, highmindedneſs, you be out of the light and out of the way, in corners, and out of the pure relation, we have a witneſs in your conſcience againſt thoſe things, which lets you ſee what you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172706:5"/>and will let you profeſſe no more if to it you hearken, which turns from the world and the relations therein, for all who beleeve not the light, and are not to it come, have a love, but it is in the world; and a relation, but it is in the world, which is enmity to God, ſo that relation which is enmity is denied with the light, that love which is enmity, is denied with the light, which leads to the pure relation, which envres not, where the deſtroyer, and devourer is rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe faith of ſuch no better then the faith of the Phariſees who onely believe of a Chriſt, becauſe the Scriptures declare of him, but the faith of them who dwel in the life and power of God and follow the Lamb who therſoever he goes, is that faith wch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> overcomes the world, to believe of a Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare of him, is to believe as the Phariſees did believe, who were the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors and murderers of the juſt, but to believe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> light, the life that gave forth the Scriptures is ſeen, and Chriſt is believed in, and here he hath the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in himſelf, and comes to be a child of light and born of God, which birth overcomes the world, and now ſaith Chriſt they hate the light becauſe their deeds are evil, and will not bring their deeds to it, becauſe the light will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, and this is the condemnation the light ſaith Chriſt; and now it doth appear them that hate the light, prieſts, teachers, people, young and old hate the light, and will not bring their deeds to the light, becauſe the light vvill reprove them, neither vvill they ſuffer other that vvalke in the light, and love the light, and bring their deeds to the Light and ſhew their dees with the light, and reprove them with the light, becauſe they hate the light, and them that walk in it, and caſt them into Priſon, and ſo are ſtumbling at the light all ſorts of people, (mark) it is the light that they hate, ſaith Chriſt, they hate the light which reproves their evil deeds, and this light is that which the world and the teachers thereof cannot endure to be talked off, but hate it and them that walk in it, &amp; it is the light that is ſo much ſtumbled at, ſo becauſe their deeds are evil, and they walk in darkneſs, there is a proof, for they that walk in the light ſtumble not, but come to receive the light of life, here Chriſts words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fulfilled amongſt them that hate the light, and will not bring their deeds to the light, becauſe the light will reprove them, for that which doth make manifeſt is light, ſo that which makes manifeſt they cannot endure, but would be in the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, and keep their deeds in the dark as it is manifeſt, and ſaith Chriſt the Divel ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon, he is out of the light out of the truth, and a lyar, and a murtherer from the beginning, which now is ſeen with the light, and trampled upon, and all that owne not the light which cometh from the word, are the wicked feeds men, ſowing abroad their tares, their lies, the evil reports, and them that are gone from the light, that comes from the word of truth, are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to believe lies and reports, and may cry up darkneſs, if you hate the light what have you to cry up elſe, if you turn from the light, pittyful preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which hates the light, which manifeſteth all the vvorks of darkneſs.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed in the</hi> 4th. <hi>month</hi> 8th. <hi>day for</hi> M. W. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
